Hello and welcome to a audio data set consisting of one single episode of a non-existent podcast.
Or, I may append this to a podcast that I set up recently regarding my with my thoughts on speech
tech and AI in particular. More AI in generative AI I would say. But in any event, the purpose of this
voice recording is actually to create a lengthy voice sample for a quick evaluation, a back of the
envelope evaluation as they might say for different speech attacks models. And I'm doing this because I
I thought I'd made a great breakthrough in my journey with speech tech. And that was succeeding in
the elusive task of fine-tuning whisper. Whisper is, and I'm going to just talk, I'm trying to
mix up, I'm going to try a few different styles of speaking. I might whisper something at some
points as well. And I'll go back to speaking loud in different parts. I'm going to send really
like a crazy person because I'm also going to try to speak at different pitches and cadences
in order to really try to push a speech attacks model through its paces, which is trying to make
sense of is this guy just rambling on and coherently in one long sentence or are these just actually
series of step standalone standalone sentences? And how is it going to handle step alone? That's not a
word. What happens when you use speech attacks and you use a fake word and then you're like, wait,
that's not actually, that word doesn't exist. How does AI handle that? And these and more are all the
questions that I'm seeking to answer in this training data. Now, why did why was it trying to
find China whisper? And what is whisper? As I said, I'm going to try to
record this at a couple of different levels of
technicality for folks who are in the normal world and not totally
stuck down the rabbit hole of AI. What you have to say is a really wonderful rabbit hole to be
to be done. It's a really interesting area and speech and voice tech is the aspect of it that
I find actually most I'm not sure I would say the most interesting because there's just so much
that is fascinating in AI. But the most that I find the most personally transformative in terms of
the impact that it's had on my daily work life and productivity and how I sort of work. And
I am persevering hard with the task of training, I guess, a good solution working for Linux.
Would you have anyone actually does listen to this not just for the training data and for the
actual content? This is this is sparked. I had, besides the fine tune not working, well that was
the failure. I used plot code because one thing these days that there is nothing
short of solving, you know, the reason of life or something that's flawed and
agentically I can't do, which is not really the case. It does seem that way sometimes but it
fails a lot as well. And this is one of those instances where last week I put together an hour
of voice training data, basically speaking just random things for three minutes and
it was actually kind of tedious because the text were really weird. Some of them were it was like,
it was AI generated. I tried before to reach Sherlock Holmes for an hour and I just couldn't,
I was so bored after 10 minutes that I was like, okay, knowing just gonna have to find something
else to read. So I used a created with AI Studio, a vibe code is a synthetic text generator,
which actually I thought was probably a better way of doing it because it would give me more
short samples with more varied content. So I was like, okay, give me a voice note. Like I'm
recording an email, give me a short story to read, give me pros to read. So I came up with all
these different things and they added a little timer to it so I could see how close I was to one
hour and I spent like an hour one afternoon or probably two hours by the time you do retakes
and whatever because you want to, it gave me a source of truth which I'm not sure if that's the
scientific way to approach this. Topic of gathering training data but I thought made sense.
I have a lot of audio data from recording voice notes which I've also kind of used
being experimenting with using for a different purpose. It's slightly different annotating
task types. It's more text classification experiment or well it's more than that actually
working on a voice app so it's a prototype I guess is really more accurate.
But you can do that and you can work backwards. You listen back to a voice note and you
painfully go through one of those transcribing where you start and stop and scrub around it and
you fix the errors but it's really really pouring to do that. So I thought it would be last tedious
in the long term if I just recorded this source of truth so it gave me these three minute snippets.
I recorded them it saved in MP3 and the TXT in the same folder and I created an error that data.
So I was very hopeful quite a little bit hopeful that I would be able that I could actually fine tune
whisper. I want to fine tune whisper because when I got into voice tech last November my wife was in
the US and I was alone at home and when crazy people like me do really wild things like use voice
to tech technology that was basically when I started doing it I didn't feel like a crazy person
speaking to myself and my expectations weren't that high. I used speech tech now and again
try it out. It's like it'd be really cool if you could just like speak into your computer and
whatever I tried out that had Linux support was just it was not good basically and this blew me away
from the first go. I mean it wasn't 100% accurate out of the box and it took work but it was good
enough that there was a solid foundation and it kind of passed that pivot point that it's actually
worth doing this. There's a point where it's so like the transcript is you don't have to get 100%
accuracy for it to be worth your time for it's speech attacks to be a worthwhile addition to your
productivity but you do need to get above let's say I don't know 85% if it's 60% or 50% you inevitably
say screw it I'll just type it because you end up missing errors in the transcript and it becomes
actually worse you end up in a worse position than you started with it that's been my experience.
So I was like oh this is actually really really good now how did that happen? The answer is
ASR with per being open-sourced and the transformer architecture if you want to go back to the
to the underpinnings which really blows my mind and it's on my list to read through that paper
all you need is attention as attentively as can be done with my limited brain because it's super
high-level stuff super advanced stuff I mean but that I think of all the things that
are fascinating about the sudden rise and AI and the dramatic capabilities I find it fascinating
a few people are like hang on you've got this thing that can speak to you like a chatbot and LLM
then you've got image generation okay so firstly those two things on the surface have nothing
in common so like how are they how did that just happen all at the same time and then when you
extend that further you're like sooner right you can sing a song an AI will like come up with
an instrumental and then you've got whisper and you're like wait a second how did all this stuff
like if it's all AI what's like there has to be some commonality otherwise these are four these
totally different technologies on the surface of it and the transformer architecture is as far as
I know the answer and I can't even say I can't even pretend that I really understand what the
transformer architecture means in depth but I have scandis and as I said I want to print it and
really kind of think over it's at some point and I'll probably feel bad about myself I think
because weren't those guys in their in their 20s like that's crazy I think I asked chat Gbt
once who were the who wrote that paper and how old were they when it was published in ARC
and I was expecting like I don't know what do you what do you imagine I personally imagine kind of
like you know you have these breakthroughs during COVID and things like that were like these kind
of really obscure scientists who are like in their 50s and they've just kind of been laboring
labs and we're really in writing and publishing and kind of obscure academic publications and they
finally like hit a big or win a Nobel Prize and then their household household names so I that
was kind of what I had in mind that was the mental image I'd formed of the birth of ARC
like I wasn't expecting 20 somethings in San Francisco though I thought that was both very very
funny very cool and actually kind of inspiring it's nice to think that people who you know just
you might put them in the kind of milieu or bubble or world that you are in are credibly in through
you know the series of connections that are coming up with such literally world changing
innovations so that was I thought anyway that that that was cool okay voice training data how
were we doing we're about 10 minutes and I'm still talking about voice technology so whisper was
brilliant and I was so excited that I was my first instinct was to like guess it's like oh my gosh
I have to get like a really good microphone for this so I didn't go on a spending spree because
I said I'm gonna have to just wait a month and see if I still use this and it just kind of became
it's become really part of my daily routine like if I'm writing an email I'll record a voice note
and then I've developed and it's nice to see that everyone is like developing the same things in
parallel like that's my kind of a weird thing to say but when I look I kind of came when I started
working on this these prototypes on GitHub which is where I just kind of share very freely and loosely
ideas and you know first iterations on concepts and for one of a better word I called it like
LLM post processing or cleanup or basically a system prompt that after you get back the raw text
from whisper you run it through model and say okay this is crappy text like add sentence structure
and you know fix it up and now when I'm exploring the different tools that are out there the people
have built I see quite a number of projects have basically you know done the same thing
less that be misconstrued I'm not saying for a millisecond that I inspired them I'm sure this
has been a thing that's been integrated into tools for a while but it's it's the kind of thing that
when you start using these tools every day the need for it is almost instantly apparent because text
that doesn't have any punctuation or progress basing takes a long time to you know it takes so
long to get it into a presentable email that again it's it moves speech tech into that
before that inflection point where you're like nah she's not worth it it's like it'll just be
quicker to type this so it's it's a big it's a little touch that actually is a big deal
so I was on whisper and I've been using whisper and I kind of early on find a couple of tools
I couldn't find what I was looking for on Linux which is basically just something that'll run
in the background you'll give it an API key and it'll just like transcribe
with like a little key to start and start the dictation and the issues where I discovered that
like most people involved in creating these projects were very much focused on local models
and running whisper locally because you can and I tried that a bunch of times and just never
got results that were as good as the cloud and when I began looking at the cost of the speech
text API is what I was spending I just thought there is it's actually in my opinion just one of
the better deals in API spending and in cloud like it's just not that expensive for very very good
models that are much more you know you're going to be able to run the full model the latest model
versus whatever you can run on your average GPU unless you want to buy a crazy GPU it doesn't
really make sense to me and I privacy is another concern that I know is kind of like a very much
a separate thing that people just don't want their voice data and their voice leaving their
local environment maybe for regulatory reasons as well but I'm not in that I'm neither really
care about people listening to my grocery list consisting of reminding myself that I need to buy
more beer cheetos and hummus which is kind of the three three staples of my diet during periods of
poor nutrition but the kind of stuff that I transcribe most it's just not it's not a it's not a
privacy thing I'm that sort of sensitive about and I don't do anything so you know sensitive
or secure that requires airgapping so I looked at the pricing and especially the kind of older
models mini some of them are very very affordable and I did it back to the I did a calculation once
with Chachi BT and I was like okay this is the this is the API price for I can't remember whatever
the model was let's say I just go at it like nonstop which rarely happens probably I would say an
average I might dictate 30 to 60 minutes per day if I was probably summing up the emails documents
outlines which is a lot but it's it's still a fairly modest amount and I was like well some days I
do go on like one or two days where I've been usually when I'm like kind of out of the house and
just have something like I've nothing else to do like if I'm at a hospital we have a newborn
and you're waiting for like eight hours and hours for an appointment and I would probably have
listened to podcasts before becoming a speech fanatic and I'm like oh wait let me just get down
let me just get these ideas out of my head and that's when I'll go on my speech spinges but those
are like ones every few months like not frequently but I said okay let's just say if I'm gonna price
out cloud sgt if I was like dedicated every second of every waking hour to transcribing for some
odd reason I mean it have to like ease and use the toilet like you know there's only so many hours
I'm awake for so like let's just say a maximum of like 40 hour 45 minutes in the hours and I said
all right let's just say 50 who knows you're dictating on the toilet we do it so you could just do 60
but whatever I did and every day like you're going flat out seven days a week dictating nonstop
as like what's my monthly API bill gonna be at this price and it came out to like seven to your
80 bucks and I was like well that would be an extraordinary amount of dictation and I would hope
that there was some compelling reason more worth more than 70 dollars that I embarked upon that
so given that that's kind of the max point for me I said that's actually very very affordable
now you're gonna if you want to spec out the costs and you want to do the post processing
that I really do feel as valuable that's gonna cost more as well on a less you're using
Gemini which needless to say is a random person sitting in Jerusalem I have no affiliation nor with
Google nor anthropic nor Gemini nor any major tech vendor for that matter um I like Gemini
not so much as a everyday model um it's kind of underwhelmed in that respect I would say
but for multimodal I think it's got a lot to offer and I think that the transcribing functionality
whereby it can um process audio with the system prompt and both give you a transgression that's
cleaned up that reduces two steps to one and that for me is a very very big deal and uh I feel like
even Google hasn't really sort of thought through how useful the that modality is more kind of
use cases uh you can achieve with it because I found in the course of this year just an endless
list of really kind of system prompt system prompt stuff that I can say okay I've used it
for a capture context data for AI which is literally I might speak for if I wanted to have a good
bank of context data about who knows my childhood uh more realistically maybe my career goals
something that would just be like really boring to type out so I'll just like sit in my car
and record it for 10 minutes and that's 10 minutes you get a lot of information in um emails which is
short text uh just there is a whole bunch and all these workflows kind of require a little bit
of treatment afterwards and different treatment my context pipeline is kind of like just extract the
bare essential so you end up with me talking very loosely about sort of what I've done in my career
where I've worked where my light to work and it goes it condenses that down to very robotic language
that is easy to chunk parts and maybe put into a vector database Daniel has worked in technology
Daniel is a has been working in martino stuff like that that's not how you would speak um but I
figure it's probably easier to parse for after all robots so we've almost got to 20 minutes and this
is actually a success because I waste 20 minutes of my uh of the evening speaking into microphone and
the levels were shot and it uh it was clipping and I said I can't read you an evaluation I have to
be fair I have to give the models a chance to do their thing uh what am I hoping to achieve in this
okay my fine shun was a dud as mentioned deep gram sdt I'm really really hopeful that this prototype
will work and it's a built in public open source so anyone is welcome to use it if I make anything good
but that was really exciting for me last night when after hours of um try my own prototype seeing
someone just made something that works like that you know you're not going to have to build a custom
condo environment and image I have AMD GPU which makes things much more complicated I didn't find it
and I was about to give up and I said all right let me just give deep grams Linux thing a shot
and if this doesn't work um I'm just going to go back to trying to vibe code something myself
and when I ran the script I was using cloud code to do the installation process
it ran the script and oh my gosh it works just like that uh the tricky thing
for all those ones and all the nitty-ditty-ditty-gritty details um was that I don't think it was actually
struggling with transcription but pasting wailant makes life very hard and I think there was
something not running at the right time anyway deep gram I looked at how they actually handled
that because it worked out in the box when other stuff didn't and it was quite a clever little mechanism
and but more so than that the accuracy was brilliant now what am I doing here this is going to be a 20
minute audio uh sample and I'm I think I've done one or two of these before but I did it with
sure snappy voice notes this is kind of long form this actually might be a better approximation
for what's useful to me than voice memos like I need to buy three
beaters of moat tomorrow and peter bread which is probably how like half my voice note
voice notes sound like if anyone were to I don't know like find my phone they'd be like this is
the most boring person in the world although actually there are some like kind of uh journaling
thoughts as well but it's a lot of content like that and the probably for the evaluation the most
useful thing is slightly obscure tech github new cleano hugging face not so obscure that it's not
going to have a chance of knowing it but hopefully sufficiently well known that the models should get
it uh I tried to do a little bit of speaking really fast and speaking very slowly I would say in
general I've spoken deliver this at a faster pace than I usually would go into strong coffee
flowing through my bloodstream and the thing that I'm not going to get into spanish mark is
background noise which is my first take that I had to get rid of my wife come in with my son
and for a good night kiss and that actually would have been super helpful to get in because it was
non-diarray sorry if we had diarrayization a female I could say I want the male voice and that
wasn't intended for transcription um and we're not going to get background noise like people
hunking their horns which is something I've done in my main data set where I am trying to go back
to some of my voice notes annotate them and run a benchmark but this is going to be just a pure
quick test and as someone I'm working on a voice note idea that's my sort of end
motivation besides thinking it's an absolute outstanding technology that's coming to
viability and really I know the same as cheesy can actually have a very transformative effect
it's you know voice technology has been life changing for folks living with
disabilities and I think there's something really nice about the fact that it can also benefit
you know folks who are able bodies and like we can all in different ways
um make this tech as useful as possible regardless of the exact way that we're using it um and I
think there's something very powerful in that and it can be very cool um I see huge potential what
excites me about voice tech a lot of things actually firstly the fact that it's cheap and accurate
as I mentioned at the very start of this um and it's getting better and better with stuff like
accent handling um I'm not sure my fight my fine tune will actually ever come to fruition in the
sense that I'll use it day to day as I imagine and get likes you per flawless words error rates because
I'm just kind of skeptical about local speech attacks as I mentioned and I think the pace of
innovation and improvement in the models the main reasons for fine tuning from what I've seen
have been people who are something that really blows blows my mind about ASR is the idea that it's
inherently ailing you or multilingual phonetic based so as folks who use speak very obscure languages
that there may be there there might be a positive training data or almost none at all and therefore
the accuracy is significantly reduced or folks in very critical environments I know there are
you this is used extensively in medical transcription and dispatch your work as um you know the call
sentries who send out ambulances etc where accuracy is absolutely paramount and in the case of doctors
radiologists they might be using very specialized vocab all the time so those are kind of the main
two things and I'm not sure that really just for trying to make it better on a few random tech words
with my slightly I mean I have an accent but like not you know an accent that a few other million
people have ish I'm not sure that my little fine tune is going to actually like the bump in
word error reduction if I ever actually figure out how to do it and get it up to the cloud by the
time we've done that I suspect that the next generation of ASR will just be so good that it will
kind of be well that would be cool for a dive but I'll just use this instead so that's going to be
is for today's episodes of voice training data single long shot evaluation who am I going to
compare whisper is always good as a benchmark but I'm more interested in seeing whisper head-to-head
with two things really one is whisper variance so you've got these projects like faster whisper
distilled whisper it's a bit confusing there's a whole bunch of them and the emerging ASRs which
are also a thing my intention for this is I'm not sure I'm going to have the time in any point
of the foreseeable future to go back to this whole episode and create a proper source truth or I fix
everything might do it if I can get one transcriptions that's sufficiently close to perfection
but what I would actually love to do on hogging face I think would be a great probably how I might
visualize this is having the audio waveform play and then have the transcript for each model below
it and maybe even a like you know two scale and maybe even a local one as well like local whisper
versus open AI API etc and I can then actually listen back to segments or anyone who wants to
can listen back to segments of this recording and see where a particular model to struggle
with others didn't as well as the sort of headline finding of which had the best WER but that would
require the source of truth okay that's it hope this was I don't know maybe useful for other
folks interested in STT you want to see that I always feel think I've just said as something I
didn't intend to STT I said for those isn't carefully including hopefully the models themselves
this has been myself Daniel Rosal for more um jumbled repositories about my uh roving interests
in AI but particularly agentic mcp and voice tech you can find me on github hogging face
where else daniel rosal dot com which is my personal website as well as this podcast whose name
I sadly cannot remember until next time thanks for listening