Hello and welcome to a audio dataset consisting of one
single episode of a nonexistent podcast.
Or it I may append this to a podcast that
I set up recently regarding my with my thoughts on
speech tech and A.
I.
In particular, more A.
And generative A.
I.
I would I would say.
But in any event, the purpose of this voice recording
is actually to create a lengthy voice sample for a
quick evaluation, a back of the envelope evaluation, they might
say, for different speech attacks models.
I'm doing this because I thought I'd made a great
breakthrough in my journey with speech tech and that was
succeeding in the elusive task of fine tuning whisper.
Whisper is, and I'm to just talk, I'm trying to
mix up.
I'm going to try a few different styles of speaking
whisper something at some points as well.
And I'll go back to speaking loud in in different
parts are going to sound really like a crazy person
because I'm also going to try to speak at different
pitches and cadences in order to really try to push
a speech to text model through its paces, which is
trying to make sense of is this guy just rambling
on incoherently in one long sentence or are these just
actually a series of step standalone, standalone, standalone sentences?
And how is it going to handle step alone?
That's not a word.
What happens when you use speech to text and you
use a fake word?
And then you're like, wait, that's not actually that word
doesn't exist.
How does AI handle that?
And these and more are all the questions that I'm
seeking to answer in this training data.
Now, why was I trying to fine tune Whisper?
And what is Whisper?
As I said, I'm going to try to record this
at a couple of different levels of technicality for folks
who are in the normal world and not totally stuck
down the rabbit hole of AI, which you have to
say is a really wonderful rabbit hole to be done.
It's a really interesting area and speech and voice tech
is is the aspect of it that I find actually
most I'm not sure I would say the most interesting
because there's just so much that is fascinating in AI.
But the most that I find the most personally transformative
in terms of the impact that it's had on my
daily work life and productivity and how I sort of
work.
I'm persevering hard with the task of trying to get
a good solution working for Linux, which if anyone actually
does listen to this, not just for the training data
and for the actual content, is sparked.
I had, besides the fine tune not working, well that
was the failure.
I used Claude code because one thinks these days that
there is nothing short of solving, you know, the the
reason of life or something that clause and agentic AI
can't do, which is not really the case.
It does seem that way sometimes, but it fails a
lot as well.
And this is one of those instances where last week
I put together an hour of voice training data, basically
speaking just random things for three minutes.
It was actually kind of tedious because the texts were
really weird.
Some of them were, it was like it was AI
generated.
I tried before to read Sherlock Holmes for an hour
and I just couldn't, I was so bored after ten
minutes that I was like, okay, no, I'm just gonna
have to find something else to read.
So I used a created with AI Studio, VibeCoded, a
synthetic text generator which actually I thought was probably a
better way of doing it because it would give me
more short samples with more varied content.
So I was like, okay, give me a voice note
like I'm recording an email, give me a short story
to read, give me prose to read.
So I came up with all these different things and
they added a little timer to it so I could
see how close I was to one hour.
And I spent like an hour one afternoon or probably
two hours by the time you do retakes and whatever
because you want to it gave me a source of
truth which I'm not sure if that's the scientific way
to approach this topic of gathering training data but I
thought made sense.
I have a lot of audio data from recording voice
notes which I've also kind of used, been experimenting with
using for a different purpose.
Slightly different annotating task types.
It's more a text classification experiment or Well, it's more
than that actually.
I'm working on a voice app.
So it's a prototype, I guess, is really more accurate.
But you can do that and you can work backwards.
Listen back to a voice note and you painfully go
through one of those transcribing, where you start and stop
and scrub around it and you fix the errors, but
it's really, really pouring to do that.
So I thought it would be less tedious in the
long term if I just recorded the source of truth.
So it gave me these three minutes snippets.
I recorded them and saved an MP3 and a TXT
in the same folder and I created an error that
data.
So I was very hopeful, quietly, a little bit hopeful
that I would be able, that I could actually fine
tune Whisper.
I want to fine tune Whisper because when I got
into voice tech last November, my wife was in the
US and I was alone at home.
And when crazy people like me do really wild things
like use voice to tech technology.
That was basically when I started doing it, I didn't
feel like a crazy person speaking to myself.
And my expectations weren't that high.
I'd used speech tech now and again, tried it out.
I was like, it'd be really cool if you could
just like speak into your computer and whatever I tried
out that had Linux support was just, it was not
good basically.
And this blew me away from the first go.
I mean, it wasn't one hundred percent accurate out of
the box and it took work, but it was good
enough that there was a solid foundation and it kind
of passed that pivot point that it's actually worth doing
this.
You know, there's a point where it's so like, the
transcript is you don't have to get one hundred percent
accuracy for it to be worth your time for speech
to text to be a worthwhile addition to your productivity.
But you do need to get above, let's say, I
don't know, eighty five percent.
If it's sixty percent or fifty percent, you inevitably say,
Screw it, I'll just type it.
Because you end up missing errors in the transcript and
it becomes actually worse.
You end up in a worse position than you started
with it.
That's been my experience.
So I was like, Oh, this is actually really, really
good now.
How did that happen?
And the answer is ASR, Whisper being open sourced and
the transformer architecture, if you want to go back to
the underpinnings, which really blows my mind and it's on
my list to read through that paper.
All you need is attention as attentively as can be
done with my limited brain because it's super super high
level stuff, super advanced stuff, mean.
That I think of all the things that are fascinating
about the sudden rise in AI and the dramatic capabilities,
I find it fascinating that few people are like, hang
on, you've got this thing that can speak to you
like a chatbot, an LLM.
And then you've got image generation.
Okay.
So firstly, two things on the surface have nothing in
common.
So how did that just happen all at the same
time?
And then when you extend that further, you're like, Suno.
You can sing a song and AI will come up
with an instrumental.
And then you've got Whisper and you're like, Wait a
second.
How did all this stuff If it's all AI, there
has to be some commonality.
Otherwise, are totally different technologies on the surface of it.
And the transformer architecture is, as far as I know,
the answer.
And I can't even say, can't even pretend that I
really understand what the transformer architecture means in-depth.
But I have scanned this and as I said, I
want to print it and really kind of think over
it at some point.
And I'll probably feel bad about myself, I think, because
weren't those guys in twenties?
Like, that's crazy.
I think I asked ChatGPT once who wrote that paper
and how old were they when it was published in
ArcSiv?
And I was expecting like, I don't know, what do
you imagine?
I personally imagine kind of like, you you have these
breakthroughs during COVID and things like that, where like these
kind of really obscure scientists who are in their 50s
and they've just kind of been laboring in labs and
wearily in writing and publishing in kind of obscure academic
publications.
And they finally hit a big or win a Nobel
Prize and then their household names.
So that was kind of what I had in mind.
That was the mental image I'd formed of the birth
of ArcSim.
Like I wasn't expecting twenty somethings in San Francisco.
I thought that was both very funny, very cool, and
actually kind of inspiring.
It's nice to think that people who just you might
put them in the kind of milieu or bubble or
world that you are in incredibly in through a series
of connections that are coming up with such literally world
changing innovations.
So that was I thought anyway, that's that that was
cool.
Okay.
Voice training data.
How are we doing?
We're about ten minutes, and I'm still talking about voice
technology.
So Whisper was brilliant, and I was so excited that
my first instinct was to guess, like, Oh my gosh,
I have to get a really good microphone for this.
So I didn't go on a spending spree because I
said, I'm gonna have to just wait a month and
see if I still use this.
And it just kind of became it's become really part
of my daily routine.
Like if I'm writing an email, I'll record a voice
note and then I've developed and it's nice to see
that everyone is like developing the same things in parallel.
That's kind of a weird thing to say, when I
started working on these prototypes on GitHub, which is where
I just kind of share very freely and loosely ideas
and first iterations on concepts.
And for want of a better word, I called it
like LLM post processing or clean up or basically a
system prompt that after you get back the raw text
from Whisper, you run it through a model and say,
okay, this is crappy text like add sentence structure and,
you know, fix it up.
And now when I'm exploring the different tools that are
out there that people have built, I see quite a
number of projects have basically done the same thing.
Lest that be misconstrued, I'm not saying for a millisecond
that I inspired them.
I'm sure this has been a thing that's been integrated
into tools for a while, but it's the kind of
thing that when you start using these tools every day,
the need for it is almost instantly apparent because text
that doesn't have any punctuation or paragraph spacing takes a
long time to, you know, it takes so long to
get it into a presentable email that again, moves speech
tech into that before that inflection point where you're like,
nah, it's just not worth it.
It's like, it'll just be quicker to type this.
So it's a big, it's a little touch that actually
is a big deal.
So I was on Whisper and I've been using Whisper
and I kind of early on found a couple of
tools.
I couldn't find what I was looking for on Linux,
which is basically just something that'll run-in the background.
You'll give it an API key and it will just
like transcribe with like a little key to start and
stop the dictation.
And the issues where I discovered that like most people
involved in creating these projects were very much focused on
local models, running Whisper locally because you can.
And I tried that a bunch of times and just
never got results that were as good as the cloud.
And when I began looking at the cost of the
speech to text APIs and what I was spending, I
just thought there is it's actually, in my opinion, just
one of the better deals in API spending in the
cloud.
Like, it's just not that expensive for very, very good
models that are much more, you know, you're gonna be
able to run the full model, the latest model versus
whatever you can run on your average GPU unless you
want to buy a crazy GPU.
It doesn't really make sense to me.
Privacy is another concern that I know is kind of
like a very much a separate thing that people just
don't want their voice data and their voice leaving their
local environment maybe for regulatory reasons as well.
But I'm not in that.
I neither really care about people listening to my, grocery
list, consisting of, reminding myself that I need to buy
more beer, Cheetos, and hummus, which is kind of the
three staples of my diet during periods of poor nutrition.
But the kind of stuff that I transcribe, it's just
not.
It's not a privacy thing I'm that sort of sensitive
about and I don't do anything so sensitive or secure
that requires air capping.
I looked at the pricing and especially the kind of
older model mini.
Some of them are very, very affordable and I did
a calculation once with ChatGPT and I was like, okay,
this is the API price for I can't remember whatever
the model was.
Let's say I just go at it like nonstop, which
rarely happens.
Probably, I would say on average I might dictate thirty
to sixty minutes per day if I was probably summing
up the emails, documents, outlines, which is a lot, but
it's it's still a fairly modest amount.
And I was like, well, some days I do go
on like one or two days where I've been usually
when I'm like kind of out of the house and
just have something like I have nothing else to do.
Like if I'm at a hospital, we have a newborn
and you're waiting for like eight hours and hours for
an appointment.
And I would probably have listened to podcasts before becoming
a speech fanatic.
And I'm like, Oh, wait, let me just get down.
Let me just get these ideas out of my head.
And that's when I'll go on my speech binges.
But those are like once every few months, like not
frequently.
But I said, okay, let's just say if I'm going
to price out cloud STT.
If I was like dedicated every second of every waking
hour to transcribing for some odd reason, I mean I'd
have to eat and use the toilet.
There's only so many hours I'm awake for.
So let's just say a maximum of forty five minutes
in the hour, then I said, All right, let's just
say fifty.
Who knows?
You're dictating on the toilet.
We do it.
So you could just do sixty, but whatever I did
and every day, like you're going flat out seven days
a week dictating nonstop.
I was like, What's my monthly API bill going to
be at this price?
And it came out to like seventy or eighty bucks.
And I was like, Well, that would be an extraordinary
amount of dictation.
And I would hope that there was some compelling reason
worth more than seventy dollars that I embarked upon that
project.
So given that that's kind of the max point for
me I said that's actually very very affordable.
Now you're gonna if you want to spec out the
costs and you want to do the post processing that
I really do feel is valuable, that's going to cost
some more as well.
Unless you're using Gemini, which needless to say is a
random person sitting in Jerusalem.
I have no affiliation nor with Google nor Anthropic nor
Gemini nor any major tech vendor for that matter.
I like Gemini not so much as a everyday model.
It's kind of underwhelmed in that respect, I would say.
But for multimodal, I think it's got a lot to
offer.
And I think that the transcribing functionality whereby it can,
process audio with a system prompt and both give you
transcription that's cleaned up.
That reduces two steps to one.
And that for me is a very, very big deal.
And I feel like even Google hasn't really sort of
thought through how useful the that modality is and what
kind of use cases you can achieve with it.
Because I found in the course of this year just
an endless list of really kind of system prompt stuff
that I can say, okay, I've used it to capture
context data for AI, which is literally I might speak
for if I wanted to have a good bank of
context data about who knows my childhood.
More realistically, maybe my career goals, something that would just
be like really boring to type out.
So I'll just like sit in my car and record
it for ten minutes.
And that ten minutes you get a lot of information
in.
Emails, which is short text.
Just there is a whole bunch.
And all these workflows kind of require a little bit
of treatment afterwards and different treatment.
My context pipeline is kind of like just extract the
bare essentials.
You end up with me talking very loosely about sort
of what I've done in my career, where I've worked,
where I might like to work.
And it goes, it condenses that down to very robotic
language that is easy to chunk parse and maybe put
into a vector database.
Daniel has worked in technology.
Daniel has been working in, know, stuff like that.
That's not how you would speak, but I figure it's
probably easier to parse for, after all, robots.
So we've almost got to twenty minutes and this is
actually a success because I wasted twenty minutes of my
of the evening speaking into you in microphone and the
levels were shot and was clipping and I said I
can't really do an evaluation.
I have to be fair.
I have to give the models a chance to do
their thing.
What am I hoping to achieve in this?
Okay, my fine tune was a dud as mentioned.
Deepgram STT, I'm really, really hopeful that this prototype will
work and it's a build in public open source so
anyone is welcome to use it if I make anything
good.
But that was really exciting for me last night when
after hours of trying my own prototype, seeing someone just
made something that works like that, you you're not gonna
have to build a custom conda environment and image.
I have AMD GPU which makes things much more complicated.
I didn't find it and I was about to give
up and I said, All right, let me just give
Deepgram's Linux thing a shot.
And if this doesn't work, I'm just gonna go back
to trying to vibe code something myself.
And when I ran the script, I was using Cloud
Code to do the installation process, it ran the script
and, oh my gosh, it works just like that.
The tricky thing for all those who wants to know
all the nitty, ditty, nitty gritty details was that I
don't think it was actually struggling with transcription, but pasting
Weyland makes life very hard.
And I think there was something not running at the
right time.
Anyway, Deepgram, I looked at how they actually handle that
because it worked out of the box when other stuff
didn't.
And it was quite a clever little mechanism.
And but more so than that, the accuracy was brilliant.
Now what am I what am I doing here?
This is gonna be a twenty minute audio sample.
And I'm I think I've done one or two of
these before, but I did it with short, snappy voice
notes.
This is kind of long form.
This actually might be a better approximation for what's useful
to me than voice memos.
Like, I need to buy three liters of milk tomorrow
and peter bread, which is probably how half my voice
notes sound.
Like if anyone were to find my phone they'd be
like this is the most boring person in the world.
Although actually there are some journaling thoughts as well, but
it's a lot of content like that.
And the probably for the evaluation, the most useful thing
is slightly obscure tech, GitHub, Nucleano, hugging face, not so
obscure that it's not gonna have a chance of knowing
it, but hopefully sufficiently well known that the model should
get it.
I tried to do a little bit of speaking really
fast and speaking very slowly.
Would say in general, I've spoken, delivered this at a
faster pace than I usually would owing to strong coffee
flowing through my bloodstream.
And the thing that I'm not gonna get in this
benchmark is background noise, which in my first take that
I had to get rid of, my wife came in
with my son and for a good night kiss.
And that actually would have been super helpful to get
in because it was non diarized or if we had
diarization.
A female, I could say, I want the male voice
and that wasn't intended for transcription.
And we're not going to get background noise like people
honking their horns, which is something I've done in my
main data set where I am trying to go back
to some of my voice notes, annotate them and run
a benchmark.
But this is going to be just a pure quick
test.
And as someone I'm working on a voice note idea.
That's my sort of end motivation besides thinking it's an
absolutely outstanding technology that's coming to viability.
And really, I know this sounds cheesy, can actually have
a very transformative effect.
Voice technology has been life changing for folks living with
disabilities.
And I think there's something really nice about the fact
that it can also benefit folks who are able-bodied and
we can all in different ways make this tech as
useful as possible regardless of the exact way that we're
using it.
And I think there's something very powerful in that, and
it can be very cool.
I see huge potential.
What excites me about voice tech?
A lot of things actually.
Firstly, the fact that it's cheap and accurate, as I
mentioned at the very start of this, and it's getting
better and better with stuff like accent handling.
I'm not sure my fine tune will actually ever come
to fruition in the sense that I'll use it day
to day as I imagine.
I get like superb, flawless words error rates because I'm
just kind of skeptical about local speech to text, as
I mentioned.
And I think the pace of innovation and improvement in
the models, the main reasons for fine tuning from what
I've seen have been people who are something that really
blows blows my mind about ASR is the idea that
it's inherently ailingual or multilingual, phonetic based.
So as folks who use speak very obscure languages that
there may be very there might be a paucity of
training data or almost none at all, and therefore the
accuracy is significantly reduced.
Or folks in very critical environments, I know there are
this is used extensively in medical transcription and dispatcher work
as, you know the call centers who send out ambulances
etc.
Where accuracy is absolutely paramount and in the case of
doctors radiologists they might be using very specialized vocab all
the time.
So those are kind of the main two things, and
I'm not sure that really just for trying to make
it better on a few random tech words with my
slightly I mean, I have an accent, but, like, not,
you know, an accent that a few other million people
have ish.
I'm not sure that my little fine tune is gonna
actually like, the bump in word error reduction, if I
ever actually figure out how to do it and get
it up to the cloud, by the time we've done
that, I suspect that the next generation of ASR will
just be so good that it will kind of be,
well, that would have been cool if it worked out,
but I'll just use this instead.
So that's gonna be it for today's episode of voice
training data.
Single, long shot evaluation.
Who am I gonna compare?
Whisper is always good as a benchmark, but I'm more
interested in seeing Whisper head to head with two things
really.
One is Whisper variants.
So you've got these projects like Faster Whisper.
Distill Whisper.
It's a bit confusing.
There's a whole bunch of them.
And the emerging ASRs, which are also a thing.
My intention for this is I'm not sure I'm gonna
have the time in any point in the foreseeable future
to go back to this whole episode and create a
proper source truth where I fix everything.
Might do it if I can get one transcription that's
sufficiently close to perfection.
But what I would actually love to do on Hugging
Face, I think would be a great probably how I
might visualize this is having the audio waveform play and
then have the transcript for each model below it and
maybe even a, like, you know, to scale and maybe
even a local one as well, like local whisper versus
OpenAI API, etcetera.
And I can then actually listen back to segments or
anyone who wants to can listen back to segments of
this recording and see where a particular model struggled and
others didn't as well as the sort of headline finding
of which had the best W E R but that
would require the source of truth.
Okay, that's it.
I hope this was, I don't know, maybe useful for
other folks interested in STT.
You want to see I always think I've just said
it as something I didn't intend to.
STT, I said for those.
Listen carefully, including hopefully the models themselves.
This has been myself, Daniel Rosol.
For more jumbled repositories about my roving interest in AI
but particularly AgenTic, MCP and VoiceTech you can find me
on GitHub.
Hugging Face.
Where else?
DanielRosel dot com, which is my personal website, as well
as this podcast whose name I sadly cannot remember.
Until next time.
Thanks for listening.