Hello and welcome to a audio data
set consisting of one single
episode of a non-existent podcast.
Or it, uh, I may append this to a
podcast that I set up recently.
Um, regarding my, uh,
with my thoughts on speech,
tech and AI in particular,
more AI and generative AI, I would,
uh, I would say, but in any event,
the purpose of this, um,
voice recording is actually to create
a lengthy voice sample for a quick
evaluation, a back of the envelope
evaluation, as they might say,
for different speech to text models.
And I'm doing this because I,
uh, I thought I'd made a great
breakthrough in my journey with
speech tech, and that was succeeding
in the elusive task of fine tuning.
Whisper, whisper is.
And I'm going to just talk.
I'm trying to mix up, uh,
I'm going to try a few different
styles of speaking.
I might whisper something at
some point as well,
and I'll go back to speaking loud in,
uh, in different parts.
I'm going to sound really like a
crazy person, because I'm also
going to try to speak at different
pitches and cadences in order to
really try to put a speech to
text model through its paces,
which is trying to make sense of,
is this guy just on incoherently in
one long sentence, or are these just
actually a series of step standalone,
standalone, standalone sentences?
And how is it going to handle
step alone? That's not a word.
Uh, what happens when you use
speech to text and you use a fake
word and then you're like, wait,
that's not actually that word doesn't
exist. How does AI handle that?
And, uh, these and more are all
the questions that I'm seeking
to answer in this training data.
Now, why did why was it trying
to fine tune a whisper?
And what is whisper?
As I said, I'm gonna try to, uh,
record this at a couple of different
levels of technicality for folks who
are, uh, you know, in the normal, uh,
world and not totally stuck down
the rabbit hole of AI, uh, which I
have to say is a really wonderful,
uh, rabbit hole to be to be down.
Um, it's a really interesting area.
And speech and voice tech is is
the aspect of it that I find
actually most.
I'm not sure I would say the most
interesting, because there's just
so much that is fascinating in AI.
Uh, but the most that I find the
most personally transformative
in terms of the impact that it's
had on my daily work life and
productivity and how I sort of work.
And I'm persevering hard with the
task of trying to guess a good
solution working for Linux, which if
anyone actually does listen to this,
not just for the training data
and for the actual content, uh,
this is this is has sparked I had
besides the fine tune not working.
Well, that was the failure.
Um, I used clod code because one
thinks these days that there is
nothing short of solving,
you know, the, uh,
the reason of life or something.
Uh, that clod and agentic AI can't
do, uh, which is not really the case.
Uh, it does seem that way sometimes,
but it fails a lot as well.
And this is one of those, uh,
instances where last week I put
together an hour of voice training
data, basically speaking just
random things for three minutes.
And, um,
it was actually kind of tedious
because the texts were really weird.
Some of them were it was like it
was AI generated.
Um, I tried before to read
Sherlock Holmes for an hour and
I just couldn't.
I was so bored, uh,
after ten minutes that I was like,
okay, now I'm just gonna have to
find something else to read.
So I used a created with AI
studio vibe coded.
A synthetic text generator.
Um, which actually I thought was
probably a better way of doing it
because it would give me more short
samples with more varied content.
So I was like, okay, give me a voice
note, like I'm recording an email,
give me a short story to read,
give me prose, um, to read.
So I came up with all these
different things, and I added a
little timer to it so I could
see how close I was to one hour.
Um, and, uh, I spent like an hour one
afternoon or probably two hours by
the time you, um, you do retakes
or whatever because you want to.
It gave me a source of truth,
which I'm not sure if that's the
scientific way to approach this topic
of gathering, uh, training data,
but I thought it made sense.
Um, I have a lot of audio data
from recording voice notes,
which I've also kind of used, um,
been experimenting with using for
a different purpose, slightly
different annotating task types.
It's more text classification
experiment or uh, well,
it's more than that, actually.
I'm working on a voice app,
so it's a prototype I guess is
really more accurate.
Um, but you can do that and you
can work backwards.
You're like,
you listen back to a voice note
and you painfully go through one
of those transcribing, you know,
where you start and stop and scrub
around it and you fix the errors.
But it's really,
really boring to do that.
So I thought it would be less
tedious in the long term if I just
recorded The Source of truth.
So it gave me these three minute
snippets.
I recorded them and saved an MP3
and a txt in the same folder,
and I created an hour of that data.
Uh, so I was very hopeful, quietly,
you know, a little bit hopeful
that I would be able that I could
actually fine tune, whisper.
Um, I want to fine tune whisper
because when I got into voice tech
last November, my wife was in
the US and I was alone at home.
And you know, when crazy people
like me do really wild things like
use voice to tech, uh, technology.
That was basically, um,
when I started doing it,
I didn't feel like a crazy person
speaking to myself, and my
expectations weren't that high.
Uh, I used speech tech now and again.
Um, tried it out.
I was like, it'd be really cool
if you could just, like,
speak into your computer.
And whatever I tried out that
had Linux support was just.
It was not good, basically.
Um, and this blew me away from
the first go.
I mean, it wasn't 100% accurate
out of the box and it took work,
but it was good enough that there was
a solid foundation and it kind of
passed that, uh, pivot point that
it's actually worth doing this.
You know, there's a point where
it's so like the transcript is you
don't have to get 100% accuracy
for it to be worth your time for
speech to text to be a worthwhile
addition to your productivity.
But you do need to get above.
Let's say, I don't know, 85%.
If it's 60% or 50%,
you inevitably say, screw it.
I'll just type it because you end up
missing errors in the transcript
and it becomes actually worse.
You end up in a worse position
than you started with.
And that's been my experience.
So, um, I was like, oh,
this is actually really, really good.
Now how did that happen?
And the answer is ASR whisper
being open sourced and the
transformer architecture,
if you want to go back to the,
um, to the underpinnings, which
really blows my mind and it's on my
list to read through that paper.
Um, all you need is attention as
attentively as can be done with my
limited brain because it's super,
super high level stuff.
Um, super advanced stuff.
I mean, uh, but that I think of all
the things that are fascinating
about the sudden rise in AI and
the dramatic capabilities.
I find it fascinating that few
people are like, hang on,
you've got this thing that can speak
to you like a chatbot, an LLM,
and then you've got image generation.
Okay, so firstly, those two things on
the surface have nothing in common.
Um, so like how are they how did that
just happen all at the same time.
And then when you extend that
further, um, you're like sooner,
right?
You can sing a song and AI will like,
come up with an instrumental and then
you've got whisper and you're like,
wait a second,
how did all this stuff, like,
if it's all AI, what's like there
has to be some commonality.
Otherwise these are four.
These are totally different
technologies on the surface of it.
And, uh, the transformer architecture
is, as far as I know, the answer.
And I can't even say can't even
pretend that I really understand
what the transformer
architecture means in depth,
but I have scanned it and as I said,
I want to print it and really kind
of think over it at some point,
and I'll probably feel bad about
myself, I think,
because weren't those guys in their
in their 20s like, that's crazy.
I think I asked ChatGPT once who
were the who wrote that paper
and how old were they when it
was published in arXiv?
And I was expecting like,
I don't know,
what do you what do you imagine?
I personally imagine kind of like,
you know,
you have these breakthroughs during
Covid and things like that where
like these kind of really obscure
scientists who are like in their
50s and they've just kind of been
laboring in labs and, uh, wearily
and writing in publishing in kind
of obscure academic publications.
And they finally, like,
hit a big or win a Nobel Prize and
then their household household names.
Uh, so that was kind of what I
had in mind.
That was the mental image I'd
formed of the birth of arXiv.
Like, I wasn't expecting 20
somethings in San Francisco,
though I thought that was both very,
very funny, very cool,
and actually kind of inspiring.
It's nice to think that people who,
you know, just you might put them
in the kind of milieu or bubble or
world that you are in or credibly in,
through, you know,
a series of connections that are
coming up with such literally
world changing, um, innovations.
Uh, so that was, I thought,
anyway, that, that that was cool.
Okay. Voice training data.
How are we doing?
We're about ten minutes, and I'm
still talking about voice technology.
Um, so whisper was brilliant,
and I was so excited that I was.
My first instinct was to, like,
get like, oh, my gosh,
I have to get, like,
a really good microphone for this.
So, um, I didn't go on a
spending spree because I said,
I'm gonna have to just wait a
month and see if I still use this.
And it just kind of became it's
become really part of my daily
routine.
Like, if I'm writing an email,
I'll record a voice note.
And then I've developed and it's
nice to see that everyone is
like developing the same things
in parallel.
Like, that's kind of a weird thing
to say, but when I look, I kind of
came when I started working on this,
these prototypes on GitHub,
which is where I just kind of
share very freely and loosely,
uh, ideas and, you know,
first iterations on, on concepts,
um, and for want of a better word,
I called it like, uh,
lm post-processing or cleanup or
basically a system prompt that after
you get back the raw text from
whisper, you run it through a model
and say, okay, this is crappy text,
like add sentence structure and,
you know, fix it up.
And, um, now when I'm exploring the
different tools that are out there
that people have built, I see, uh,
quite a number of projects have
basically done the same thing,
um, less that be misconstrued.
I'm not saying for a millisecond
that I inspired them.
I'm sure this has been a thing that's
been integrated into tools for a
while, but it's it's the kind of
thing that when you start using these
tools every day, the need for it
is almost instantly apparent, uh,
because text that doesn't have any
punctuation or paragraph spacing
takes a long time to, you know,
it takes so long to get it into
a presentable email that again,
it's it's it moves speech tech
into that before that inflection
point where you're like, no,
it's just not worth it.
It's like it'll just be quicker
to type this.
So it's a big it's a little touch.
That actually is a big deal.
Uh, so I was on whisper and I've
been using whisper and I kind of
early on found a couple of tools.
I couldn't find what I was
looking for on Linux, which is,
um, basically just something
that'll run in the background.
You'll give it an API key and it
will just transcribe. Um.
with, like, a little key to
start and stop the dictation.
Uh, and the issues were I discovered
that, like most people involved in
creating these projects were very
much focused on local models running
whisper locally, because you can.
And I tried that a bunch of
times and just never got results
that were as good as the cloud.
And when I began looking at the
cost of the speech to text APIs
and what I was spending,
I just thought there's it's actually,
in my opinion, just one of the better
deals in API spending and in cloud.
Like it's just not that expensive
for very, very good models that are
much more, you know, you're going
to be able to run the full model,
the latest model versus whatever
you can run on your average GPU.
Unless you want to buy a crazy GPU.
It doesn't really make sense to me.
Now, privacy is another concern.
Um, that I know is kind of like a
very much a separate thing that
people just don't want their voice,
data, and their voice leaving
their local environment,
maybe for regulatory reasons as well.
Um, but I'm not in that.
Um, I'm neither really care about
people listening to my, uh,
grocery list consisting of, uh,
reminding myself that I need to
buy more beer, Cheetos and hummus,
which is kind of the three,
three staples of my diet.
Um, during periods of poor nutrition.
Uh, but the kind of stuff that I
transcribe, it's just not it's not a,
it's not a privacy thing and that
sort of sensitive about and, uh,
I don't do anything so,
you know, sensitive or secure,
that requires air gapping.
So, um, I looked at the pricing and
especially the kind of older models,
mini, um, some of them are very,
very affordable.
And I did a back of the I did a
calculation once with ChatGPT
and I was like, okay, this is a,
this is the API price for I can't
remember whatever the model was.
Uh, let's say I just go at it
like nonstop,
which it rarely happens. Probably.
I would say on average,
I might dictate 30 to 60 minutes per
day if I was probably summing up
the emails, documents, outlines,
um, which is a lot, but it's it's
still a fairly modest amount.
And I was like, well,
some days I do go on like 1 or 2
days where I've been.
Usually when I'm like kind of out of
the house and just have something
like, I have nothing else to do.
Like if I'm at a hospital with a
newborn, uh, and you're waiting
for like eight hours and hours
for an appointment, and I would
probably have listened to podcasts
before becoming a speech fanatic.
And I'm like, oh, wait,
let me just get down.
Let me just get these ideas out
of my head.
And that's when I'll go on my
speech binges.
But those are like once every
few months, like not frequently.
But I said, okay, let's just say
if I'm gonna price out.
Cloud asked if I was like, dedicated
every second of every waking hour to
transcribing for some odd reason. Um.
I mean, it'd have to, like,
eat and use the toilet and,
like, you know, there's only so
many hours I'm awake for.
So, like,
let's just say a maximum of, like,
40 hours, 45 minutes in the hour.
Then I said, all right,
let's just say 50. Who knows?
You're dictating on the toilet.
We do it.
Uh,
so it could be you could just do 60.
But whatever I did, and every day,
like, you're going flat out seven
days a week dictating non-stop.
I was like, what's my monthly API
bill going to be at this price?
And it came out to like 70 or 80
bucks.
And I was like, well, that would be
an extraordinary amount of dictation.
And I would hope that there was
some compelling reason,
more worth more than $70,
that I embarked upon that project.
Uh, so given that that's kind of the
max point for me, I said, that's
actually very, very affordable.
Um, now you're gonna if you want
to spec out the costs and you want
to do the post-processing that I
really do feel is valuable.
Um, that's going to cost some more as
well, unless you're using Gemini,
which, uh, needless to say, is a
random person sitting in Jerusalem.
Uh, I have no affiliation,
nor with Google, nor anthropic,
nor Gemini, nor any major tech vendor
for that matter. Um, I like Gemini.
Not so much as a everyday model.
Um, it's kind of underwhelmed in
that respect, I would say.
But for multimodal,
I think it's got a lot to offer.
And I think that the transcribing
functionality whereby it can,
um, process audio with a system
prompt and both give you
transcription that's cleaned up,
that reduces two steps to one.
And that for me is a very,
very big deal.
And, uh, I feel like even Google
has haven't really sort of thought
through how useful the that
modality is and what kind of use
cases you can achieve with it.
Because I found in the course of
this year just an endless list
of really kind of system prompt,
system prompt stuff that I can say,
okay, I've used it to capture context
data for AI, which is literally I
might speak for if I wanted to have a
good bank of context data about,
who knows, my childhood.
Uh, more realistically,
maybe my career goals, uh,
something that would just be,
like, really boring to type out.
So I'll just, like, sit in my car
and record it for ten minutes.
And that ten minutes,
you get a lot of information in,
um, emails, which is short text.
Um, just there is a whole bunch.
And all these workflows kind of
require a little bit of treatment
afterwards and different treatment.
My context pipeline is kind of like
just extract the bare essentials.
So you end up with me talking very
loosely about sort of what I've done
in my career, where I've worked,
where I might like to work,
and it goes it condenses that
down to very robotic language
that is easy to chunk, parse,
and maybe put into a vector database.
Daniel has worked in technology,
Daniel is a has been working in,
you know, stuff like that.
That's not how you would speak.
Um, but I figure it's probably easier
to parse for, after all, robots.
So we've almost got to 20 minutes.
And this is actually a success
because I wasted 20 minutes of my,
uh, of the evening speaking into
a microphone, and, uh,
the levels were shot and, uh, it,
uh, it was clipping and I said,
I can't really do an evaluation.
I have to be fair.
I have to give the models a
chance to do their thing.
Uh,
what am I hoping to achieve in this?
Okay, my fine tune was a dud,
as mentioned Deepgram SVT.
I'm really, really hopeful that
this prototype will work.
And it's a built in public open
source, so anyone is welcome to
use it if I make anything good.
Um, but that was really exciting for
me last night when after hours of,
um, trying my own prototype,
seeing someone just made
something that works like that.
You know,
you're not going to have to build a
custom conda environment and image.
I have AMD GPU, which makes
things much more complicated.
I didn't find it and I was about
to give up and I said,
all right, let me just give deep
grams Linux thing a shot.
And if this doesn't work, um,
I'm just going to go back to
trying to code something myself.
And when I ran the script,
I was using cloud code to do the
installation process.
It ran the script and oh my gosh,
it works just like that.
Uh, the tricky thing for all those
who wants to know all the nitty
gritty, nitty gritty details, um, was
that I don't think it was actually
struggling with transcription, but
pasting Wayland makes life very hard,
and I think there was something not
running in the right time anyway.
Deepgram I looked at how they
actually handle that because it
worked out of the box when other
stuff didn't, and it was quite a
clever little mechanism,
and but more so than that,
the accuracy was brilliant.
Now, what am I doing here?
This is going to be a 20 minute
audio sample, and I'm I think
I've done 1 or 2 of these before,
but I did it with short, snappy voice
notes. This is kind of long form.
This actually might be a better
approximation for what's useful
to me than voice memos.
Like I need to buy three liters
of milk tomorrow, and pita bread,
which is probably how like half
my voice voice notes sound like
if anyone were to, I don't know,
like find my phone,
they'd be like, this is the most
boring person in the world.
Although actually there are some
like kind of, uh,
journaling thoughts as well.
But it's a lot of content like that.
And the probably for the evaluation,
the most useful thing is slightly
obscure tech GitHub uh, hugging face
not so obscure that it's not going
to have a chance of knowing it,
but hopefully sufficiently well
known that the model should get it.
I tried to do a little bit of
speaking really fast and
speaking very slowly.
I would say in general,
I've spoken, delivered this at a
faster pace than I usually would
owing to strong coffee flowing
through my bloodstream.
And the thing that I'm not going
to get in this benchmark is
background noise, which in my first
take that I had to get rid of,
my wife came in with my son and
for a good night kiss.
And that actually would have
been super helpful to get in
because it was not diarised.
Or if we had diarisation a female,
I could say I want the male
voice and that wasn't intended
for transcription.
Um, and we're not going to get
background noise like people
honking their horns,
which is something I've done in my
main data set where I am trying to
go back to some of my voice notes,
annotate them, and run a benchmark.
But this is going to be just a
pure quick test.
And as someone I'm working on a
voice note idea,
that's my sort of end motivation.
Besides thinking it's an
absolutely outstanding technology
that's coming to viability.
And really, I know this sounds
cheesy can actually have a very
transformative effect.
Um, it's, you know, voice technology
has been life changing for, uh,
folks living with, um, disabilities.
And I think there's something
really nice about the fact that
it can also benefit, you know,
folks who are able bodied and like,
we can all in different ways, um,
make this tech as useful as possible,
regardless of the exact way that
we're using it.
Um, and I think there's something
very powerful in that, and it can be
very cool. Um, I see use potential.
What excites me about voice tech?
A lot of things, actually.
Firstly, the fact that it's cheap
and accurate, as I mentioned at
the very start of this, um,
and it's getting better and better
with stuff like accent handling, um,
I'm not sure my, my fine tune will
actually ever come to fruition in the
sense that I'll use it day to day,
as I imagine I get like superb,
flawless word error rates because I'm
just kind of skeptical about local
speech to texts, as I mentioned.
And I think the pace of innovation
and improvement in the models,
the main reasons for fine tuning from
what I've seen have been people who
are something that really blows,
blows my mind about ASR is the idea
that it's inherently a lingual
or multilingual phonetic based.
So as folks who use speak very
obscure languages that there may
be there might be a paucity of
training data or almost none at all,
and therefore the accuracy is
significantly reduced or folks
in very critical environments.
I know there are.
This is used extensively in medical
transcription and dispatcher work as,
um, you know, the call centers who
send out ambulances, etc., where
accuracy is absolutely paramount.
And in the case of doctors,
radiologists, they might be using
very specialized vocab all the time.
So those are kind of the main
two things.
And I'm not sure that really just for
trying to make it better on a few
random tech words with my slightly.
I mean, I have an accent, but like,
not, you know, an accent that a few
other million people have. Ish.
I'm not sure that my little fine
tune is going to actually like the
bump in word error rate reduction.
If I ever actually figure out how
to do it and get it up to the
cloud by the time I've done that.
I suspect that the next
generation of ASR will just be
so good that it will kind of be.
Ah, well,
that would be cool if it worked out,
but I'll just use this instead.
So that's going to be it for today's
episode of, uh, voice training data.
Single long shot evaluation.
Who am I going to compare?
Whisper is always good as a
benchmark, but I'm more
interested in seeing Whisperer
head to head with two things,
really. One is whisper variance.
So you've got these projects like
faster Whisper, Still whisper.
It's a bit confusing.
There's a whole bunch of them
and the emerging acers,
which are also a thing.
My intention for this is I'm not
sure I'm going to have the time
in any point in the foreseeable
future to go back through this whole
episode and create a proper source,
truth or a fix.
Everything might do it if I can
get one transcription that
sufficiently close to perfection.
But what I would actually love
to do on Hugging Face I think
would be a great.
Probably how I might visualize this
is having the audio waveform play,
and then have the transcript for each
model below it, and maybe even a,
um, like, you know, two scale and
maybe even a local one as well,
like local whisper versus open
AI API, Etc. and, um, I can then
actually listen back to segments
or anyone who wants to can listen
back to segments of this recording
and see where a particular model
struggled and others didn't, as well
as the sort of headline finding
of which had the best, uh, wer.
But that would require the source
of truth. Okay. That's it.
Hope this was, I don't know,
maybe useful for other folks
interested in stuff you want to see.
I always feel think I've just said
something I didn't intend to say.
I said for those, listen carefully.
Including, hopefully,
the models themselves.
This has been myself,
Daniel Rosehill, for more, um,
jumbled repositories about my,
uh, roving interest in AI,
but particularly Agentic,
MCP and voice tech.
Uh, you can find me on GitHub.
Hugging face. Where else?
Daniel, which is my personal website,
as well as this podcast whose
name I sadly cannot remember.
Until next time.
Thanks for listening.