Hello and welcome to a audio data set consisting of one single episode of a non-existent podcast.
Or, I may append this to a podcast that I set up recently regarding my
with my thoughts on speech tech and AI in particular. More AI in generative AI, I would say.
But in any event, the purpose of this voice recording is actually to create a lengthy voice
sample for a quick evaluation of back of the envelope evaluation as they might say for
different speech attacks models. And I'm doing this because I thought I had made a great breakthrough
in my journey with speech tech and that was succeeding in the elusive task of fine-tuning whisper.
Whisper is, and I'm going to just talk, I'm trying to mix up, I'm going to try a few different
styles of speaking, I might whisper something at some points as well. And I'll go back to
speaking loud in a different part. So I'm going to send really like a crazy person because I'm also
going to try to speak at different pitches and cadences in order to really try to put
a speech attacks model through its pieces, which is trying to make sense of, is this guy just
ramling on and coherently in one long sentence or are these just actually a series of
step of standalone, standalone, standalone sentences. And how is it going to handle
step alone? That's not a word. What happens when you use speech attacks and you use a fake word.
And then you're like, wait, that's not actually that word doesn't exist. How does AI handle that? And
these and more are all the questions that I'm seeking to answer in this training data. Now,
why was it trying to find you to whisper? And what is whisper, as I said, I'm going to try to
record this at a couple of different levels of technicality for folks who are in the normal
world and not totally stocked down the rabbit hole of AI. What you have to say is a really wonderful
rabbit hole to be, to be done. It's a really interesting area and speech and voice attack is the
aspect of it that I find actually most, I'm not sure I would say the most interesting because there's
just so much that is fascinating in AI. But the most that I find the most personally transformative
in terms of the impact that it's had on my daily work life and productivity and how I sort of work.
And I'm persevering hard with the task of training, yes, a good solution working for Linux.
Would you have anyone actually, does listen to this not just for the training data and for the actual
content? This is this is sparked. I had, besides the fine tune not working. Well, that was the failure.
I used Claude Codes because one thing's these days that there is nothing sort of solving
you know, the reason of life or something at that's flawed and agentic AI can't do, which is not really
the case. It does seem that way sometimes, but it fails a lot as well. And this is one of those
instances where last week I put together an hour of voice training data.
Basically speaking just random things for three minutes and it was actually kind of tedious because
the texts were really weird. Some of them were it was like AI generated. I tried before
to reach Sherlock Holmes for an hour and I just couldn't, I was so bored after 10 minutes that I was
okay knowing just gonna have to find something out to read. So I used a created with AI Studio
vibe code as a synthetic text generator, which actually I thought was probably a better way of
doing it because it would give me more short samples with more varied content. So I was like okay,
give me a voice note like I'm recording an email, give me a short story to read, give me pros
to read. So I came up with all these different things and they added a little timer to it so I
could see how to let us say well as to one hour. And I spent like an hour, one afternoon or probably
two hours by the time you do retakes on whatever because you want to, it gave me a source of truth
which I'm not sure if that's the scientific way to approach this topic of gathering training data,
but I thought made sense. I have a lot of audio data from recording voice notes which I've also
kind of used being experimenting with using for a different purpose. It's slightly different
annotating task types. It's more text classification experiment or well it's more than that actually
I'm working on a voice app so it's a prototype I guess is really more accurate. But you can do that
and you can work backwards. You listen back to a voice note and you painfully go through one of those
transcribing where you start and stop and scrub around in a new fixie areas but it's really
really pouring to do that. So I thought it would be less tedious in the long term if I just
recorded this source of truth. So it gave me these three minutes snippets. I recorded them
it saved an MP3 and a TXT in the same folder and I created an error that data. So I was very hopeful
that I could actually find you in whisper. I want to find you in whisper because when I got
into voice tech last November my wife was in the US and I was alone at home and when crazy
people like me do really wild things like use voice tech technology that was basically when I
started doing it I didn't feel like a crazy person speaking to myself and my expectations weren't
that high. I used speech tech now and again tried to write as like it would be really cool if you
just like speak into your computer and whatever I tried I used that had Linux support was just
it was not good basically and this blew me away from the first go. I mean it wasn't 100%
accurate either the box and it took work but it was good enough that there was a solid foundation
and it kind of passed that pivot point that it's actually worth doing this. There's a point where
it's so like the transcript is you don't have to get 100% accuracy for it to be worth your time
for it's speech tech to be worth while it isn't your productivity but you do need to get above
let's say 85%. If it's 60% or 50% you inevitably say screw it I'll just type it because you
end up missing errors in the transcript and it becomes actually worse you end up in a worse position
than you started with that's been my experience. So I was like oh this is actually really really good
now how did that happen? The answer is ASR whisper being open sourced and the transformer
architecture if you want to go back to the to the underpinnings which really blows my mind and it's
on my list to reto that paper all you need is attention as attentively as can be done with my limited
brain because it's super super high level stuff super advanced stuff I mean but that I think of all the
things that are fascinating about the sudden rise and AI and the dramatic capabilities I find
fascinating a few people are like hang on you've got this thing that can speak to you like a chatbot
and LLM and then you've got image generation okay so first of all those two things
on the surface have nothing in common so like how did that just happen all at the same time and
then when you extend that further you're like Suno right you can sing a song an AI will like come
up with an instrumental and then you've got whisper and you're like wait a second how did all this
stuff like if it's all AI what's like there has to be some commonality otherwise these are
for these are totally different technologies on the surface of it and the transformer architecture
is as far as I know the answer and I can't even say you can't even pretend that I really understand
what the transformer architecture means in depth but I have scandice and as I said once a
printed I'm really kind of think over it's at some point and I'll probably feel bad about myself
I think because when those guys in the in their 20s like that's crazy I think I asked
you to be one who were the who wrote that paper and how old were they when it was published in
arcs of I was expecting like I don't know what do you imagine I personally imagine kind of like
you know you have these breakthroughs during Covid and things like that were like these kind of
really obscure scientists who are like in their 50s and they've just kind of been laboring labs
and we're really in writing and publishing and kind of obscure academic publications and they
finally like hit a bake or when a noble apprise and then their household names so that was kind
of what I had that was the mental image I'd formed of the birth of arcs of like I wasn't
expecting 20 somethings in San Francisco though I thought that was both very very funny very cool
and actually kind of inspiring it's nice to think that people who you know just you might put them
in the kind of milieu or bubble or world that you are in or incredibly in through you know
the series of connections that are coming up with such literally world changing innovations
so that was I thought anyway that that that was cool okay voice training data how are we doing
we're at by 10 minutes and I'm still talking about voice technology so whisper was brilliant and
I was so excited that I was my first instinct was to like guess like oh my gosh I have to
get like a really good microphone for this so I didn't go on a spending spree because I said
I'm gonna have to just wait a month and see if I still use this and it just kind of became
it's become really part of my daily routine like if I'm writing an email I'll record a voice note
and then I've developed and it's nice to see that everyone is like developing the same
things in parallel like that's my kind of a weird thing to say but when I look I kind of came
when I started working on this these prototypes on GitHub which is where I just kind of share
very freely and loosely ideas and you know first iterations on concepts and for one of
a better word I called it like LLM post processing or cleanup or basically a system prompt that
after you get back the raw text from whisper you run it through model and say okay this is crappy
text like add sentence structure and you know fix it up and now when I'm exploring
the different tools that are out there the people of built I see quite a number of projects have
basically you know done the same thing last that we missed construit I'm not saying for a
millisecond that I inspired them I'm sure this has been a thing that's been integrated into tools
for a while but it's it's the kind of thing that when you start using these tools every day
the need for it is almost instantly apparent because text that doesn't have any punctuation or
paragraph spacing takes a long time to you know it takes so long to get it into a presentable email
that again it's it moves speech tech into that before that inflection point we're like that's just
not worth it it's like it's just be quicker to type this so it's it's a big it's a little touch that
actually is a big deal so I was on whisper and I've been using whisper and I kind of early on
find a couple of tools I couldn't find what I was looking for on Linux which is basically just
something that'll run in the background you'll give it an API key and it'll just like transcribe
with like a little key to start and start the dictation and the issues where I discovered
that like most people involved in creating these projects were very much focused on local models
running whisper locally because you can and I tried that a bunch of times and just never got
results that were as good as the cloud and when I began looking at the cost of the speech tech
to API is what I was spending I just thought there is it's actually in my opinion just one of the
better deals in API spending and in cloud like it's just not that expensive for very very good
models that are much more you know you're going to be able to run the full model the latest model
versus whatever you can run on your average GPU unless you want to buy crazy GPU it doesn't really
make sense to me and I've been a lot of things that I know is kind of like a very much
just everything the people just don't want their voice data and their voice leaving their local
environment maybe for regular few reasons as well but I'm not in that I'm neither really care
about people listening to my gross readest consisting of reminding myself that I need to buy more
beer cheetos and hummus which is kind of the three three staples of my diet during periods of
poor nutrition but the kind of stuff that I transcribe it's just not it's not a it's not a
privacy thing that sort of sensitive about and I don't do anything so you know sensitive or
secure that requires air capping so I looked at the pricing and especially the kind of older
model mini some of them were very very affordable and I did it back the I did a calculation once
with chatchewet and I was like okay this is the API price for I can't remember whatever the model
was let's say I just go out at like nonstop which really happens probably I would say an average
I might dictate 30 to 60 minutes per day if I was probably summing up the emails
documents outlines which is a lot but it's still a fairly modest amount and I was like well
some days I do go on like one or two days right being usually when I'm like kind of I'd do the
house and just have something like I've nothing else to do like if I met a hospital we've a newborn
and you're waiting for like eight hours and hours for an appointment and I would probably have
listened to podcasts before becoming a speech fanatic and I'm like oh wait let me just get down let me
just get these ideas out of my head and that's when I'll go on my speech spinches but those
were like once every few months like not frequently but I said okay let's just say if I'm going
to price out cloud STT if I was like dedicated every second of every waking hour to transcribing
for some odd reason I mean it have to like ease and use the toilet like you know there's only so many
hours I'm awake for so like let's just say a maximum of like 40 hour 45 minutes in the hour
then I said all right let's just say 50 who knows you're dictating on the toilet we do it
so you could just do 60 but whatever I did and every day like you're going flat out seven days
a week dictating nonstop it's like what's my monthly API bill gonna be at this price and it came
out to like 70 or 80 bucks and I was like well that would be an extraordinary amount of dictation
and I would hope that there were some compelling reason more worth more than 70 dollars that I
embarked upon their project so given the dots kind of the max point for me I said that's actually
very very affordable now you're gonna if you want to specide the costs and you want to do the post
processing that I really do feel as valuable that's gonna cost them more as well on the last
you're using Gemini which needless to say is a random person sitting in Jerusalem I have no
affiliation nor with Google nor anthropic nor Gemini nor any major tech vendor for that matter
I like Gemini not so much as a everyday model it's kind of underwhelmed in that respect I would say
but for multi-model I think it's got a lot to offer and I think that the transcribing functionality
whereby it can process audio with the system prompt and both give you transcription that's cleaned
up that reduces two steps to one and that for me is a very very big deal and I feel like even Google
hasn't really sort of thought through how useful the downloadability is more kind of use cases
you can achieve with it because I found in the course of this year just an endless list of
really kind of system prompt system prompt stuff that I can say okay I've used the trick
capture context data for AI which is literally I might speak for if I wanted to have a good bank
of context data about who knows my childhood more realistically maybe my career goals
something that would just be like really boring to type out so I'll just like sit in my car
and record it for 10 minutes and that's 10 minutes you get a lot of information in emails which
is short text just there is a whole bunch and all these workflows kind of require a little bit
of treatment afterwards and different treatment my context pipeline is kind of like just to
extract the bare essential so you end up with me talking very loosely about sort of what
I've done in my career where I've worked where my light work and it goes it condenses that down
to very robotic language that is easy to chunk parse and maybe put into a vector database
Daniel has worked in technology Daniel is a has been working in Martin you know stuff like that
that's not how you would speak but I figure it's probably easier to parse for after all robots
so we've almost got to 20 minutes and this is actually a success because I waste 20 minutes of my
of the evening speaking into my headphone and the levels were a shot and it was clipping and I said
I can't read each and evaluation I have to be fair I have to give the models a chance to do their thing
at what am I hoping to achieve in this okay my function was a daughter's mentioned
Deep Gram STT I'm really really hopeful that this prototype will work and it's a build and
public open source so anyone is welcome to use it if I make anything good but that was really exciting
for me last night when after hours of trying my own prototype seeing someone just made something that
works like that you know you're not going to have to build a custom condo environment and image
I have AMD GPU which makes things much more complicated I didn't find it and I was about to
give up and I said all right let me just give deep grams Linux thing a shot and if this doesn't work
I'm just going to go back to trying to vibe code something myself and when I ran the script
I was using cloud code to do the installation process it ran the script and oh my gosh it works just like that
the tricky thing for all those who wants to know all the nitty ditty degree nitty gritty details
was that I don't think it was actually struggling with transcription but pasting
wailant makes life very hard and I think there was something not running in the right time anyway
Deep Gram I looked at how they actually handled that because it worked out of the box one other stuff
didn't and it was quite a clever little mechanism and but more and so it's not the accuracy was brilliant
now what am I doing here this is going to be a 20 minutes audio sample and I'm I think I've done
one or two of these before but I did this with sure snappy voice notes this is kind of long form
it's actually might be a better approximation for what's useful to me than voice mammals like I
need to buy three beaters of moke tomorrow and Peter bread which is probably how like half my voice
note send like if anyone were to I don't know like find my phone they be like this is the most
boring person in the world although actually there are some like kind of journaling thoughts as well
but it's a lot of content like that and the probably for the evaluation the most useful thing is
slightly obscure tech get hub the clean hooking face not so obscure that is not going to have a chance
of knowing it but hopefully sufficiently well known that the models should get us I tried to do a
little bit of speaking really fast and speaking very slowly I would say in general I've spoken
delivered this at a faster pace than I usually would owe into strong coffee if flowing through my bloodstream
and the thing that I'm not going to get into spent work is background noise which in my first
take that I had to get rid of my wife come in with my son and for a good night kiss and that actually
would have been super helpful to get in because it was non-diorized or if we had diorization
a female I could say I want the male voice and that wasn't intended for transcription
and I'm not going to get background noise like people honking their horns which is something
of done to my main data set where I am trying to go back to some of my voice notes
and I take them and run a benchmark but this is going to be just a pure quick test and
someone working on a voice note idea that's my sort of end motivation besides thinking it's
an astudiate standing technology that's coming to viability and really I know the same it's cheesy
can actually have a very transformative effect it's you know voice technology has been life changing
for folks living with disabilities and I think there's something really nice about the fact that
it can also benefit you know folks who are able bodies and like we can all in different ways
make this tech as useful as possible regardless of the exact way that we're using it
and I think there's something very powerful in that and it can be very cool I see
huge potential what excites me about voice tech a lot of things actually
firstly the fact that it's cheap and accurate as I mentioned at the very start of this
and it's getting better and better with stuff like accent handling
I'm not sure my fine tune will actually ever come to fruition in the sense that I'll use it
day to day as I imagine and get likes you per flawless words error rates because I'm just kind of
skeptical about local speech attacks as I mentioned and I think the pace of innovation and
improvement in the models the main reason for fine tuning from what I've seen
have been people who are something that really blows my mind about ASR is the idea that it's inherently
alien fuel or multilingual fanatic based so as folks who use speak very obsturately languages
that there might be a policy of training data or almost none at all and therefore the accuracy
is significantly reduced or folks in very critical environments I know they're you this is
using extensively in medical transcription and dispatcher work as you know the call centers
use send out ambulances etc where accuracy is absolutely paramount and in the case of doctors
radiologists there might be using very specialized vocab all the time so those are kind of the main
two things and I'm not sure that really just for training make it better on a few random
tech words with my slightly I mean I have an accent but like not you know an accent that a few
other million people have ish I'm not sure that my little fine tune is going to actually
like the bump in word error reduction if I ever actually figure out how to do it and get it up to the
by the time I've done that I suspect that the next generation of ASR will just be so good that
it will kind of be no well that would be cool for a doubt but all this uses instead so that's
going to be is for today's episodes of voice training data single long-shaw evaluation
who am I going to compare with supposed to be a benchmark but I'm more interested in seeing whisper
head to head with two things ready one is whisper variants so you've got these projects like faster whisper
distilled whisper it's a bit confusing there's a whole bunch of them and the emerging ASR is
which are also a thing my intention for this is I'm not sure I'm going to have the time in any point
of the foreseeable future to go back to this whole episode and create a proper source true through
a fix everything might do it if I can get one transcriptions as efficiently close to perfection
but what I would actually love to do on hugging face I think would be a great
probably how I might visualize this is having the audio waveform play and then have the transcript
for each model below it and maybe even a like you know two scale and maybe even a local one as
well like local whisper versus open AI API etc and I can then actually listen back to segments
or anyone who wants to can listen back to segments of this recording and see where a particular
model struggled and others didn't as well as the sort of headline finding of which had the best
WER but that would require the source of truth okay that's it I hope this was I don't know
maybe useful for other folks interested in STT you want to see that I always feel think I've just
said something I didn't and do STT I said for those it's in carefully including hopefully the
models themselves this has been myself Daniel Rosal for more jumbled repository is about my
roving interest in AI but particularly agentic mcp and voice tech you can find me on
get up hugging face where else Daniel Rosal.com which is my personal website as well as
this podcast whose name I sadly cannot remember but the next time thanks for listening